

# Matt Harasymczuk

Bioastronautics Researcher, Pilot, Aerospace and Software Engineer, Astrobiologist. Working in ESA on Astronaut Lunar EVA.

matt@astromatt.space http://astromatt.space +48 781 111 743

## **About Matt**

Matt is a bioastronautics researcher, pilot, engineer (aerospace, software), scientist (biology, geology) skydiver, scuba diver and military combat medic (TCCC, ACLS). He currently collaborates on Moon and Mars research with European Space Agency on habitat, 3D bioprinter, photosynthetic bioink, hydroponic and aeroponic plant cultivation, polarized light influence on time perception and human time architecture. Matt graduated from project PoSSUM Scientist-Astronaut program where his main focus was on pressurized suit operations, hypoxia, human performance in micro-q and high-q environment.

#### **Education**

- 2017-2019 (expected), University of Warsaw, Master of Science, Geology with major in Geochemistry and Mineralogy
- 2016-2018 (expected), University of Warsaw, Master of Science, Biology with major in Microbiology of Extremophiles
- 2014-2017, Polish Air Force Academy, Master of Science, Aerospace and Astronautics with major in Aircraft Systems Engineering
- 2014-2015, Polish Air Force Academy, Postgraduate, Aerospace Management
- 2011-2013, Poznan University of Technology, Postgraduate, Computer Science with major in IT in Business Processes
- 2008-2011, Adam Mickiewicz University, Postgraduate, Philosophy of Human Interactions and Social Communication
- 2007-2011, Poznan University of Technology, Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science with major in Security of IT Systems

## Work Experience

#### **Moon and Mars Mission Research Collaborator**

Sep 2016 - Present (8 months), European Space Agency, ESTEC

- R&D on 3D bioprinter and photosynthetic 3D bioink materials with ESA ESTEC ACT
- Research on polarized light influence on time perception and time architecture, with ESA Advanced Concepts Team
- Building the Moon/Mars habitat facility with functional laboratory to demonstrate analog simulations and 3D printing

### Astronaut Trainer, Mission Organizer and Habitat Builder at M.A.R.S. Habitat

Jun 2016 - Present (10 months), marshub.org

- Building the habitat and laboratories
- Erected 20m height satellite communication radio-wave antenna
- Author of the software operating systems for the habitat
- Astronaut training and organization of future missions

#### Systems Engineer with 3D printing R&D

Dec 2013 - Present (3.5 years), Astro Tech

- End-to-end process of C.A.D. design for tools development using 3D printing technology
- Team-leader and technical quality assurance supervisor for 3D printed tools and printers
- Trainer in software engineering, 3D printing, portfolio, risk and priority management, leadership, team-building and communication

## Head of Software at 3D Printing R&D Department

Apr 2016 - Sep 2016 (6 months), Zortrax.com

- Management of 3 teams of engineers (software, firmware and models library website)
- Creating and management of product backlog for software and firmware for two 3D printer models
- Passing management to new director upon successfully delivering two products

## **Proces Architecture Main Specialist**

Jan 2014 - Jan 2016 (2 years), Center for Information Technology at Polish Ministry of Interior

- Leader of the first polish government organization transformation to agile software development and project management
- Project management and portfolio management (Scrum, Kanban, Lean, XP) for 11 teams in Polish Ministry
- Technical transformation (DevOps, continuous integration and continuous delivery, versioning, releasing and quality processes)

## **Software Systems Engineer (Release Manager, Developer Tools Specialist)**

Jun 2011 - Dec 2013 (2.5 years), MIH Allegro Group, Enterprise Architecture Department

- Building development ecosystem
- Supporting agile transformation
- Team leadership
- Trainer for engineering good practices, team communication, task management, process and quality assurance

#### Software Engineer

Jul 2006 - Jun 2011 (5 years), MBP sp. z o.o.

- Author of a CRM system for 2500+ users with four nines (99.9999%) SLA in since 2006

# **Analog Astronaut Experience**

- 2018 Jan, Arctic Expedition Hibernity, Crew Medical Officer
- 2017 Sep, M.A.R.S. Expedition 2, Commander, mission with visual and motion disabled crew members
- 2017 Jun, M.A.R.S. Expedition 1, Vice Commander, Crew Medical Officer
- 2016 Aug, Lunar Expedition, Astronaut, Flight Surgeon

# **Publications**

- Harasymczuk M., Kolodziejczyk A.M., Foing B. H. Operational Lessons Learned From Human-Robotic Partnership in Exogeology Analog Extravehicular Activity Simulation at Eifel Volcanic Region: ILEWG Euromoonmars. Human and Robotic Partnerships in Exploration Joint session of the Human Spaceflight and Exploration Symposia. International Astronautical Congress. Australia. 2017. Conference Paper. IAC-17,B3,6-A5.3,x41593
- Kolodziejczyk A.M., Harasymczuk M., Girardin P., Davidova L. Circadian Clock and Subjective Time Perception: a simple Open Source Application for the Analysis of Induced Time Perception in Humans. International Journal of Medical, Health, Biomedical, Bioengineering and Pharmaceutical Engineering. 19th International Conference on Time Perception and Time Consciousness. Prague, Czech Republic. 2017. Article.
- Papaj A., Weszka P., et al. **Stratospheric mission in search for the Schumann resonances first iteration.** Technical Transactions Issue 20. Fundamental Sciences Issue 2 NP. 2017. Article.
- Harasymczuk M., Foing B., Kolodziejczyk A.M. **Operational issues for geological analog simulation at Eifel volcanic region: ILLEWG EuroMoonMars.** Lunar and Planetary Science Conference 48th. Universities Space Research Association. Woodlands, TX, USA. 2017. Scientific Poster. "LPSC2017-2997. doi: 10.13140/RG.2.2.33223.70565"
- Vos H., Harasymczuk M. Kolodziejczyk A.M., et al. Field Spectroscopy, imaging and sampling at the Eifel MoonMars analogue.
  Lunar and Planetary Science Conference 48th. Universities Space Research Association. Woodlands, TX, USA. 2017. Scientific Poster. LPSC2017-2359
- Vos H., Kolodziejczyk A.M., Harasymczuk M. **Laboratory spectroscopy of minerals, water and plant biomarkers.** Lunar and Planetary Science Conference 48th. Universities Space Research Association. Woodlands, TX, USA. 2017. Scientific Poster. LPSC2017-2419
- Vos H., Harasymczuk M. VIS/NIR reflectance and fluorescence spectrometric studies of minerals, water, organics and biomarkers in MoonMars analogue samples. EGU General Assembly 2017. European Geosciences Union. Vienna, Austria. 2017. Abstract. EGU2017-1537
- Kolodziejczyk A.M., Harasymczuk M. **MoonMars Base in Poland: a Simulation Habitat and Laboratory for Research.** EGU General Assembly 2017. European Geosciences Union. Vienna, Austria. 2017. Abstract. EGU2017-1601
- Kolodziejczyk A.M., Harasymczuk M. **Terrestrialization of isolated habitats.** EGU General Assembly 2017. European Geosciences Union. Vienna, Austria. 2017. Abstract. EGU2017-1356
- Kolodziejczyk A.M., Harasymczuk M., et al. **Operational Lessons Learnt from the 2016 Lunar Expedition in Poland for Future Improvement of Analog Simulation of Lunar Environment.** (to be submitted). 2017. Article.
- Harasymczuk M., Kolodziejczyk A.M. The effect of polarized light on time perception. (to be submitted). 2017. Article.
- Harasymczuk M., Kolodziejczyk A.M. **Measuring the effect of root growth using random positioning machine.** (to be submitted). 2017. Article.
- Harasymczuk M. Astronaut training for long duration spaceflights and Extravehicular Activity. (to be submitted). 2017. Thesis.
- Harasymczuk M. **Analog missions astronaut and flight surgeon case study.** Astronomical Calendar 2016. Astronomia Nova. Czestochowa, Poland. 2016. Article.
- Harasymczuk M., Wylecial P. **Botnet analysis and protection methods.** Poznan University of Technology. Poznan, Poland. 2014. Thesis.

# **Training Courses**

- PADI Advanced Open Water Diver, Neutral Buoyancy, Rescue Diver (May, June 2017)
- Project PoSSUM Scientist-Astronaut Program (Spacesuit, Hypoxia, Micro-G, High-G, Mesosphere, Suborbital Flights) (Apr 2017)
- Survival Systems and Spacecraft Egress Instruction (Apr 2017)
- Winter Survival and Arctic Shooting course (Feb 2017)
- Online Emory School of Medicine: Emergency Medicine (Mar 2017)
- Biology: The Science of Life (Jan, Feb, Mar 2017)
- KTHx: SD2905.1x Human Spaceflight An introduction (Jan, Feb, Mar 2017)
- MITx: 7.28.3x Molecular Biology: RNA Processing and Translation (Jan, Feb, Mar 2017)
- KyotoUx: 003x The Extremes of Life: Microbes and Their Diversity (Jan, Feb, Mar 2017)
- Advanced Cardiovascular Life Support (Jan 2017)
- MITx: 16.00x Introduction to Aerospace Engineering: Astronautics and Human Spaceflight (Oct, Nov, Dec 2016)
- Tactical Combat Casualty Care (level I, II, III) medical aid in extreme situations (Mar, Jun, Aug 2016)
- PADI Open Water Diver course (Jun 2016)
- Basic Life Support (Jul 2016)
- Glider and private pilot course (2014, 2015)

# Conferences and workshops

- Stratospheric balloon flight for Extremely Low Frequencies research, member of navigation, track and recovery team (Nov 2016)
- ESA Innovation Exchange: When Space Meets Health, with brainstorming session on radiation protection
- Moon Village workshop on Architecture aspects (Nov 2016)
- Moon Village workshop on Geology aspects (Oct 2016)
- ESA ECSS European Cooperation for Space Standardization training course (Sep 2016)
- Symposium "Astronaut Preparation for Long Duration Spaceflight" (Sep 2016)
- European Rover Challenge (Sep 2015, Sep 2016)
- Poland in Space Symposium (Mar 2016)
- ESA ESMATS 2015 European Space Mechanisms and Tribology Symposium (Sep 2015)
- attendee and speaker at 100+ conferences on Computer Science

## **Community**

- Polish Parachuting Association
- Polish Rocket Society
- Poznan Flight Club

#### Interests

**Aerospace**: human space flights, extravehicular activity, manned lunar missions (Apollo Program), Moon/Mars habitat construction **Astrobiology and medicine**: extremophiles, 3D bioprinting, human space physiology, cognitive science

**Engineering and computer science:** 3D printing, artificial intelligence, machine learning, big data, data science **Physical Activity and sports:** aerobatics, flying, skydiving, water diving, sailing, skiing, squash, survival, swimming

Computer Games: Kerbal Space Program, Orbiter, X-Plane, Interkosmos

#### Social network profiles

- facebook.com/matt.harasymczuk
- twitter.com/astro\_matt
- flickr.com/astromatt
- youtube.com/MattHarasymczuk
- github.com/astromatt
- slideshare.net/astromatt
- linkedin.com/in/mattharasymczuk